[SPEAKER_00]: So, I had in mind to speak about noble friendship, like what the Buddha says about that and how to cultivate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll start with the kind of the most famous sutta about noble friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in the Saṃyutta Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's see... King Pasenadi is visiting the Buddha and he says... Dear Venerable Sir, while I was alone in seclusion, the following reflection arose in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma has been well expounded by the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is for one with good friends, good companions, good comrades, not for one with bad friends, bad companions, and bad comrades.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it is, Great King.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: This dhamma has been well-explained by me, and it is for the good... one with good friends, not for one with bad friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: On one occasion, Great King, I was living among the Sakans, where there's a town named Nagaraka.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abhiku Ananda approached me, paid homage to me, and sat down at one side and said, venerable sir, this is half the holy life, that is, good friendship, good companionship, good comradeship.
[SPEAKER_00]: When this was said, I told Abhiku Ananda, not so, Ananda, not so.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the entire holy life, Ananda, that is, good friendship, good companionship, good comradeship.
[SPEAKER_00]: When Abhiku has a good friend, a good companion, a good comrade, it is to be expected that he will develop and cultivate the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how does a bhikkhu who has a good friend, a good companion, a good comrade, develop and cultivate the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I'm sure you've heard it before, but I, myself, many, many times, heard that sutta quoted, but only part of the sutta quoted, only the first part.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where it says, and that's quoted by monks and nuns as well, in the talks, saying how the noble friendship is the entirety of the holy life, and then they wouldn't explain how, but instead go on talking about how community, company, camaraderie, in a sense, we're doing things together, we're together, together, together, together, is justifiable by that quote, which it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you carry on reading the same sutra, and then the Buddha explains how.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you take him on as a friend.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, with a friendly eye, you regard what he said could be beneficial for you, and out of that faith, in that friendship, you go forth.
[SPEAKER_02]: You never even meet the Buddha, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just heard about him and you regard him as a friend and you leave your home, become a monk out of that faith, make the effort, get the right view and you verify his teaching without ever meeting him.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing to do with sort of hanging out and spending time together.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's to do basically with having friends that know more than you in terms of the dhamma and then learning.
[SPEAKER_02]: But exactly, it says that it's based on seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you're going to learn through friendship is based on seclusion, withdrawal, sense restraint and all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's it's it's it's a it's a far cry from from from justifying community group activities and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's almost like a distinction, I think, between like sensual friendship, so to say, and this other kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, like the thing is people depend on company more often than not.
[SPEAKER_02]: The solitude is not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you're already given into that dependence, and you're ignoring your responsibility for it, you will then just look for anything remotely to justify it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the first part of that sutta serves that purpose, because you don't read the other bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's almost like an abstract friendship that the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you never meet him, you just hear about him, and you know, it's a friendly disposition, and because of that you go forth.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't mention that, because that would undermine the purpose of trying to justify, you know, being able to withstand seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost a sense of like you're... it's like... it's like almost like a... intertwined with like faith in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, that's why there's a friend... Yeah, that's exactly what he said.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's out of that... Because of that friendship, they... they trust... they develop this trust that, oh, this... this could help me.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they don't regard him with a friendly eye, in that sense, he wouldn't... he wouldn't... you know, he would look for faults.
[SPEAKER_02]: He wouldn't commit and he certainly would not have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, what he's saying, whoever wants to help you,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you perceive, oh, this could help me, that's already a form of friendship.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot not regard him as a friend.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you don't necessarily know whether it will be successful or not, the promise to help.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds then like, it's almost like an acknowledgment of a... like fundamental isolation, fundamental selfishness, because it's like, this person's a friend because they can help me, but not in that kind of way that people denigrate either.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no other way around it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you will have to start selfishly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a certain type of selfishness can result in cessation of selfishness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that type of selfishness is practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: That type of craving is craving for the understanding of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: And... what was the other one?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that type of conceit is the conceit for, you know, being an Arahant, being one of the enlightened beings.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because of that conceit, because of that craving, because of that selfishness, you actually are making the effort in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will cancel those very things, when you do it right, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other times, with people who delight in company, it always seems to me that it's like almost denying that fundamental need to be selfless.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's like one of the worst impediments.
[SPEAKER_02]: Minds, of course, provided
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of strength is practiced.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a must.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then it's the company, careless chatter, just hanging out.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's so many suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all the world talks about.
[SPEAKER_02]: How to not do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: How to avoid it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why you should not do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't be negligent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practice seclusion because... until it's too late to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh... so it's not really...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, he was... he was telling off.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha was telling off to the monks, probably attained monks, obviously not arahants, but, eh... clearly monks on the path, they were just hanging out together, sewing robes, preparing for the kathina, you know, the things that are good, seemingly.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would sort of blast them, like really, really, really sort of serious, serious telling off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just wasting their time in company.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you say, like, who's making noise, like a bunch of fishermen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, that's it, that's it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm approaching this monastery and I thought there's, like, a band of fishermen here, selling fish and sharting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the monks, supposedly, practicing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, when you... then you read the sutta later, it's not that they were crazy doing... No, they were actually sewing robes for the kathina occasion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha told them off.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, what's the purpose of your holy life?
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... See, it doesn't mean, like, oh, every getting together, like, to justify, like, hating on groups or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's your own personal issue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes people don't know how to deal with people, and they try to use solitude to justify... See, the Buddha said we should be in solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, for practice, not because you hate everybody else, and you can't live with them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because then you're just in solitude with your own hate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to discern where your motivation is rooted, as always.
[SPEAKER_02]: And once you do, then you will do the solitude rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, how, let's say, with that example, the person just hates everyone, it's not that, no, I'm gonna not hate everyone by going to be in company all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would they, like, address that issue?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you address that issue first by, as I said, by being aware of the motivation behind whether you're solitude or whether you're company.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, same, more often than not, people who try to justify the company, the community, the group, is people who don't know how to live alone.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have that side of things, but then, yeah, you have many people who just
[SPEAKER_02]: I have no social or have little social skills, so they cannot bear other people very well and don't know how to relate to it and always results in friction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then they go to solitude and quote the suttas about solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: But where is that rooted?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it in this their understanding of necessity of solitude as a basis for the practice?
[SPEAKER_02]: Nope.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's rooted in their real will towards those people they don't know how to deal with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you won't be doing it for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to find... you need to reroute your motivation into the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no like, oh, you should then stay with people, or you should then go to solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends why you do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you do it rightly, you will then go to solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is a necessary basis for you to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're in like a place like this, where there are people living together, so to speak, or...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I suppose, practical advice would be, if you are considering finding a place where you can kind of try a bit of both, that's what you need to look for.
[SPEAKER_02]: The place that would then allow you, if possible, to be in solitude, but then also have some reference point of other people.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you make sure you don't give in just... and whatever you're doing is rooted in the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems valuable to me to be able to have yourself exposed to different situations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think that's the whole idea of nisaya in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, having somebody to learn from means you're not completely on your own until you can be completely on your own.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, people who already decided that they don't want the solitude, then they would use this to justify the company in the group.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the Buddha said, you need to be prepared for it, like, you know, living in the wilderness dwellings.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have the right view, established in virtue, sense restraint, all these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they would say, okay, so, see, you must be ready for the solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so, is the company making you ready for the solitude?
[SPEAKER_02]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_02]: Hanging out with people is preparing me to be alone.
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that work?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a completely separate decision that you make.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I'm not ready for the solitude, but it doesn't mean I'm justified for company.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just means I'm not ready for the solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, make yourself ready for the solitude, through wisely using company and learning from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the rest of that sutta is, as you mentioned,
[SPEAKER_00]: By following the following method too, Ananda, it may be understood how the entire holy life is good friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: By relying on me as a good friend, Ananda, being subject to birth or freed from birth, being subject to aging or freed from aging, subject to illness or freed from illness, subject to death or freed from death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair are freed from those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: By this method, Ananda, it may be understood how the entire holy life is good friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he goes on to say further, further exhortation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, great king, you should train yourself thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will be one who has good friends, good comrades, good friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you have good friends, you should dwell with one thing for support.
[SPEAKER_00]: Diligence and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: He goes on to say that you should also exert your... all your people do the same and they're all gonna... that'll have... be for your mutual benefit and welfare and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, the good friend then is defined by the one that will... whose presence, interaction with, will result in your wisdom increasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not defined by the one that makes me feel good, or makes me feel happy, or makes me feel content.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could even be someone who does not make you feel very happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: More often than not, I think that's the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like someone who's poking you in the way you don't want to be poked.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're not acting from the point of view of your precious feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're acting out of recognition what's good for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the rhinoceros poem, when it said, unless you find a friend better or at least equal, he's no friend of yours then.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you should leave.
[SPEAKER_02]: You should not hang with those who are inferior to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it refers to the point of view of understanding and virtue and development of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's an important thing to keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, yeah, you'll just be, oh, you know, he's a good mate.
[SPEAKER_02]: I like his company, hanging out, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So he's a good friend, you see.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's another sutta that goes into exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's from, in the Gujarat Book of Eights, the sutta to Dighajanu.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just read the part that goes on the good friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha tells this guy, what is good friendship?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is for a householder, but I think it applies to anyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a case where a householder spends time with householders or their sons, young or old, accomplished in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: He speaks with them, engages them in discussion.
[SPEAKER_00]: He emulates that accomplishment in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: And likewise, with faith, generosity, and wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, as he's saying there, it's like, the whole point is to, like, kind of, pick up the signs, almost, of, like, what does it mean to be like this, and then you can see them in yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, which means you already need to be, internally, valuing virtue for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, you wouldn't pursue these people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't see them as valuable, and exactly, then you wouldn't have a discernment for the pursuit.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you want, so you recognize that virtue is worth being developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you, you know, you might try, partially,
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of successful, maybe not as much as you would want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can I improve this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, let me find those who are more virtuous than me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let me learn that from them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let me emulate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I'll be as virtuous as they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you benefited from that type of friendship.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just friendship in order to do the work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not friendship in order to make yourself feel good.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the last sutta I had is an interesting example of, like, this is a kind of like the example of a quote-unquote perfect community.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's from Madhyamakāya 31, the Mahāgauśiṅga Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aniruddha is living with two other monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha is asking how they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they each say this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a gain for me that I am living with such companions in the holy life and maintain bodily, verbal and mental acts of kindness, both openly and privately.
[SPEAKER_00]: I consider, why should I not set aside what I wish to do and do what these other ones wish to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: We are different in body, but one in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you make of that last statement?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why should I not set aside what I wish to do and do what these venerables wish to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we could... you realize that... or the monk there realizes that all three of them are pretty much highly developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter whether my point of view thinks this or his point of view thinks that.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are on the same level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter who does what.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, if we choose to do what he wants, because I could have wanted the same thing, because we are on the same level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, we are just one in the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not one in the mind because, again, they feel this deep spiritual connection.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's one in the mind because they share the same level of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means they invested the same amount of effort and the same amount of work.
[SPEAKER_02]: And got the same amount of results.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they recognize that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's such a blessing as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And easy abiding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if they don't even speak, they understand where they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, no mystical intuition or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's simply they understood each other's extents.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't have those problems that come with those kinds of imbalances.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, so, you know, externally, you cannot necessarily tell apart, but internally, having understood each other, they know exactly where they are at.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, yes, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I want to do this, he wants to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's coming from the same level of the same mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, they were all arhants, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many samādhi attainments and such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you see, like, the communal getting together was only when there was a purpose for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Preparing for the meal, or cleaning after the meal, or waiting for Pindapad to distribute the food, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't like, hey, let's get together just for the sake of company.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes on to say that, like they're saying, like, there's actually two examples.
[SPEAKER_00]: One occurs here, the other I'll mention after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, something along the lines of, like, whoever should see a vessel for drinking water, or a vessel for washing water, or for rinsing, void and empty, should set out water.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it is impossible for him to do this, he should set out water by signaling with his hand, having invited a companion to help him by movement of his hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he should not, for that reason, break out into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same thing for various kinds of duties that they would have to do at their little place where they live.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, see?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like,
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't do solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, company is justified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once company is justified, getting together for all sorts of reasons becomes justified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once company is justified, getting together for all sorts of reasons is justified, speaking is justified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all completely different things, different decisions you make on top of each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more like you should look at it the opposite way.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not ready for the solitude, but I must be ready for the solitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Until I'm ready for the solitude, sometimes we have to come together.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, at least when we come together, at least let us not speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we have to come together, and if we have to speak, well, at least speak only with the purpose of something practical needs to be said, or dhamma discussed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, instead of just justifying it further, you still want to, like, make it harder and harder to drift away from the original purpose of being alone and not speaking, in order to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's similar, like, when the Buddha instructed, eh... on his deathbed, when he asked, you know, how should we regard women?
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, don't look at them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, if you have to look at them, well, then don't talk to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you have to look at them and talk to them, well, then be mindful of the, you know, why you became a monk and sense restraint and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's, again, as I said, it's like, okay, so I have to do this, thus everything else that could come out of it is also justifiable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we have to come together, so we might as well just talk and address other things and end up finding new reasons for coming up together.
[SPEAKER_02]: And no.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you are not ready for the solitude, doesn't mean you're justified in company.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the end, like... but every five days, we, those three monks, sit together all night discussing dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: The alternative versions in the vinaya, it has the exact same thing, except their purpose is just never talk to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha chastises them as being like goats, basically, living not actually content and happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like...
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, like, how people, like, I don't know, like, live with people they hate, just by avoiding them and let go or getting along.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it does seem like, yeah, like, it's almost, it seems almost like, like, yeah, if you're gonna live in company, you should use the company for, like, actual beneficial things, not squander it in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, and it doesn't, and that is, you can also then conclude from the same point is, so, it doesn't mean any company.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, even monks, they can be vastly different, coming from vastly different backgrounds, with vastly different views on what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And some of it is more compatible, some of it... and not all of them want to learn equally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that doesn't mean you can just... or because you wear a robe... As I said, if the occasion comes,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, there is the whole etiquette, the whole seniority, which is exactly the purpose of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no friction, nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just do it professionally, follow along.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we're talking about actually living with somebody, in someone's proximity, getting together, doing things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize it requires wisdom and discernment internally, for your own sake, to be able to pass, to be able to discern this rightly, externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not just, oh, whoever you're bundled with, just, you know, make it work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you shouldn't be bundled with anyone, to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you do have to be bundled with somebody, because you're not ready for a solitude with the other, you don't have the right view, you're not your own guide, as they say, well, then, bundled with somebody, they will enable you in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, oh, this, you know, I get on with him, but he's equally ignorant as I am, and we just randomly step in the dark, thinking maybe one of us will stumble upon the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, in that sense, fundamentally, like, when it says, you know, the word kalyāṇamitta, I think you've said this much before, it's always going to be an ārya-sāvaka, so to put it, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, like, even a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if you have none, a very wholesome patujana is better than unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the, the other...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they quoted, like, oh, to learn the virtue and generosity from somebody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't confuse virtue and generosity for the practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a whole
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize you're not ready for seclusion, find a friend that will make you ready for seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, how should one then...
[SPEAKER_00]: We've mentioned, this has been mentioned before, but like, you know, one can be in seclusion amidst company.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like how the Buddha says, like a practicing monk, even when people visit him, all kinds of important people, his mind inclines still towards that seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you won't arrive at that through company.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, your mind still has to be, as the Buddha said, inclining towards seclusion and renunciation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can only develop the mind inclining in that direction by doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, once you've been doing it, once that becomes your mode of being, that seclusion, then, yes, people, kings turning up is not a disturbance, because the mind is still in that seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you will not arrive at that by never actually doing it, by staying in the company, and then justifying your kind of need of company through saying, see, I can become independent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like similar somebody who is not restrained from sensuality, is justifying their non-restraint of sensuality, and they can still practice the dhamma, and then the result of the dhamma will somehow restrain them of sensual
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Results of the dhamma are results of restraint of sensuality, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mind will incline to seclusion as a result of you practicing the seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, yes, even the company will not disturb it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, theoretically, everybody is able to develop that, but you cannot do it on the basis of the lifestyle that contradicts it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it just becomes your new normal, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it becomes... well, it becomes an excuse.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, see, the Buddha said you can be alone in the company.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, I shouldn't...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have to leave my company.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be alone in the company through being alone first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, he wouldn't say the virtue and sense restraint and seclusion comes first.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he did say that a million times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even in the actual... the first sutta you quoted on Kalanamitā, he said, so how did... what does this friendship really... oh, results in them understanding and practicing seclusion and getting the right view, as a result of their friendship.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was one story that interested me, like in the Parinibbāna Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It said, like, you know, when the Buddha was passing away, or he already passed away, I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ananda, he was only a sotāpanna at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'd been that for many, many years.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, like, he broke down and, you know, said that kind of stanza where it says, like, my mind that lost the dhamma... Oh, it was the Sariputta who died.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, was it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was aware of Sariputta died.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, oh, my mind is like clouded.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like the biggest branch of the tree dying.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like dullness and drowness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, in that sense, it sounded like he, like, maybe he hadn't fully even clarified, like, his relationship towards Sariputta in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously not.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, because, because in the same sense, it says those monks who were arahants,
[SPEAKER_02]: They were not grieving.
[SPEAKER_02]: They said, how can that which has arisen not cease?
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just an absolute matter of fact, that people will die and you, like, having feelings about it is inconceivable, once you fully understood that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the fact that he had feelings about it means he hasn't fully understood exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Company in relation with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you two have anything to bring up or mention?
[SPEAKER_00]: That was most of what I had to bring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing I could think of was that, like, often metta is translated as loving-kindness, but it's friendship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Friendliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it means non-harm.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you're unable to have your will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't mean, you know, smarmy, wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it could very well mean leaving someone alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your most friendly thing to do.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Non-interfering, non-obstructing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you know, when the Buddha talks about compassion and so on, it's... many times he describes what kind of compassion that is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a compassion of a doctor.
[SPEAKER_02]: They can help you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a compassion of a of a parent that sticks his hand into the throat of his child to pull the thing he's choking on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, he'll rip his throat up and you make him bleed, but he'll save his life.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, with the said, that's exactly what he does.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, so that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you need to start using the criteria for both friendship
[SPEAKER_02]: Instruction not based on how it makes you feel, but after, like, heavily invested effort in discerning, is this beneficial in the long run, which is better for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Being pleased now with inspirational verses from some spiritual poet, or being told, you know, the truth that might slightly offend me, but deep down I know already, yeah, it makes more sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, you will not have a spiritual friend, kalenamita, in the correct sense, unless you start developing wisdom for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you have no criteria for what a true friend is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might have met them and you got offended by them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the ones that make you feel good and tell you what you want to hear, well...
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not your friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a funny siddha, the one about, like, some guy visits the Buddha, and the Buddha tells him, like, you know, suffering is born from those who are dear, but then he doesn't like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Children are the root of suffering, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and so he goes to some gamblers and, you know, these are my friends, I like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, because they agreed with him, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I remember that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He just went to verify, you know, to people they don't tell him, but he wants to hear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, in my own practice, a lot of times, it's been like, you know, kind of hearing that you've been overlooking something, it hurts, but it's like, wow, if I hadn't, like, been, like, poked in that way, like, it's almost like a relief in the back of your mind, but there's that opportunity to be, like, rejected.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what your mind wants to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, yeah, you don't even realize how lucky.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are, that you don't have to figure it out yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the fact that, oh, yeah, I might not want to hear it, but then you realize, ah, that is exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I undo this now, then I see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was always the main problem, not seeing where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and how long would you have gone until you kind of solved where the problem was?
[SPEAKER_02]: Could be decades.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it can be for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, never.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you cannot know what you don't see.